Henri: Well, welcome everybody to
Fortress On A Hill, a podcast about
US foreign policy, anti imperialism
skepticism, and the American way of war.
I'm Henri thank you for joining us.
Today with me is, uh, a very
special guest, somebody we wanted
to talk to for, for quite a.
Um, the, the, the myth
man, the legend, Mr.
John Kiriakou.
Um, and, uh, we're gonna get to chat
with him for a while and try, you
know, uh, hear about some of, uh,
his experiences, many experiences.
Um, for anybody who doesn't know,
uh, John Kiriakou was a, a former
CIA counterterrorism officer and a
former senior investigator with the
Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
Uh, John became the.
Whistleblower indicted by the Obama
administration under the Espionage
Act, a law designed to punish spies.
He served 23 months in prison as the
result of his attempts to oppose the
Bush Administration's Torture program.
John, welcome to Fortress On A Hill.
John Kirakou: Thanks for having me.
Henri: So I, I'd, um, I'd like to
give the listeners kind of a sense
of, um, your, your overall background.
Certainly we don't have to go in
everything into, into great detail, but
I'd like to, to hear a bit about your
career, about, um, how you came to the
point that you became a, a whistleblower
and, um, what, how you see that
career now, today, looking back on it.
John Kirakou: Sure.
The second part of the, uh, of the
question is the more difficult one.
The, the easier part is I was recruited
into the CIA when I was in graduate school
at, uh, George Washington University.
I, uh, I had an advisor, a professor whom
I respected very deeply, uh, and, and I
continued to respect until, until he died.
Uh, that was Dr.
Gerald Post.
He recruited me into the cia
my second year in grad school.
And, um, I started at the c i
A the first week of January,
1990 as an analyst on Iraq.
And, um, Uh, spent the first seven
and a half years of my career working
exclusively on Iraq, including a
tour overseas in the Middle East,
working Iraqi sanctions issues.
I was in, uh, an office at
the CIA that no longer exists.
It's called, it was called the
Office of Leadership Analysis.
So my job really was to be Saddam
Hussein's classified biographer, or his
biographer for the intelligence community.
I got bored with that after seven,
seven and a half years, and so
I made a very unusual switch to
counter-terrorism operations.
Because at the time, um, I was the
only person, quite literally, I was
the only person in the c I A who
was fluent in both Greek and Arabic.
So, uh, they sent me to Athens as the,
um, counter-terrorism representative,
uh, mostly covering Arab Terrorism Abu
Organization, P F L P D F L P P F L P G
C, all those old school communist, uh, and
nationalist terrorist groups, and a Greek
group called Revolutionary Organization.
17.
I did that until, uh, the summer of
2000 and then went back to headquarters.
I was, I was, um, working, um, I
have to be careful of my language.
I was, I was training Middle
Eastern Intelligence services and
counter-terrorism operations and then
nine 11 hit and, uh, I was named,
um, the chief of Counter-Terrorism
Operations in Pakistan after nine.
Um, in that job I led a series of
raids that resulted in the capture of
Abu Zubahdah, who we believed at the
time was the number three in Al Qaeda.
He wasn't.
And, um, went back to headquarters.
On the strength of the Abu
Zubahdah capture, I got promoted
to, uh, executive assistant to
the CIA's deputy director and.
And then my final tour was at the
United Nations in New York, and I
resigned from, from New York to go
into the private Sector and then
later back into government at the uh,
Senate Foreign Relations Committee.
Henri: Um, I'm curious about your time
working and, and again, I, like you
said, I'm real careful about what you,
what you can share, but the time working
on Iraqi sanctions, um, uh, I'm curious
about, especially about that time
because it, it, you know, it in some
ways it informs the state of Iraq today
almost as much as the Iraq war does.
Um, but is there any, is there
anything that you can share
with us about, about that time?
Just kind of the, you know, the,
maybe your overall impressions of it?
John Kirakou: Yeah, it was, it
was that long period of Iraqi
sanctions that convinced me.
Number one, sanctions don't work.
And number two, they are cruel
to the point of becoming, in many
cases, crimes against humanity.
You know, I remember in the very
beginning of the sanctions regime,
beginning in August of 1990, um, the
State Department of the White House took
very seriously the notion that the Iraqi
people needed to continue receiving.
Food and medicine.
Okay, so, so they, they wrote up a
UN security council resolution 9 86,
and then the Iraqi said, well, we
need, you know, these pipes, right?
For our sewer system.
We can't deliver clean
water without these pipes.
Well, then the CIA says, wait a minute.
Those kinds of pipes are used in South
Africa to run fiber optic cable, and
you can use fiber optic cable for a
weapons of mass destruction program.
So no pipes.
Well with no pipes.
Then you get no clean water and
when you get no clean water,
people start to get sick.
And then, The US government says,
well, you know, they shouldn't be using
this much, uh, in, uh, antibiotics.
They must be doing something
with the, an antibiotics.
They're making a BW program out of it.
And the next thing you know, thousands,
tens of thousands of people, mostly
children, are dying and they're dying
as a direct result of these sanctions.
And I remember a senior officer
telling me, sanctions are always a bad.
Because they never do anything
to the person being targeted.
Saddam Hussein didn't give
a shit about sanction.
He had a very sophisticated
sanctions busting regime set up at
the American em, or at the Iraqi
Embassy in, uh, Amman, Jordan.
He had a, a cousin who was in
charge of it at the time, and
so it was only the Iraqi people.
And when I say the Iraqi people, I
mean the innocence among the Iraqi
people, women, children, minorities,
you know, Kurds, Shia, they were
the ones who were suffering.
It wasn't Saddam or his Trei clan or
his Aja family, or really any Sunnis
in the, in the power structure of
the Iraqi government and military.
None of them suffered
at all from sanctions.
The Iraqi people suffered from sanction.
Uh, you know, we renewed
sanctions so many times.
Uh, uh, after 9 86, it was 10 96,
and then it was like 1234, and it
was just year after year after year.
Sanctions were being, were being renewed.
And I remember saying to a colleague
of mine, a buddy of mine at the
time, I can't do this as a career.
Nothing's gonna change.
American policy's not gonna change, and
we're not serious about taking out Saddam,
nor should we have been because that in
and of itself would've been a violation
of international law as it was later.
Um, but I just decided I, I had to do
something different and more interesting.
And every, let me tell you, every Greek
American at the cia, all through the
CIA's history has wanted to serve in Athe.
And so that's what we all sought to do
and I ended up getting a great tour there.
Henri: I remember speaking to, um,
I did, I did two tours in Iraq as
a, as an Army mp, and I remember
speaking to, Different people.
It was usually tra uh, the translators
that we had cuz it was easier
for us to, to go back and forth.
But talking about just that, that
entire period and both, you know, the
Gulf War in and of itself, the, um,
the massive killings that happened
to those who rose up against Saddam.
Following George Bush's call.
And that was one that, this, this
particular guy I'm thinking of
that, that was a huge thing for him.
But then, and then, you know, children,
dead children, you know, from no food,
from no medicine, but in terms of trying
to understand, you know, the, the, the
totality of American involvement in Iraq
and the costs that had been paid, and I,
I, I read your, uh, your recent article
Henri (2): at Consortium News regarding
Tony Blinken pursuing Soviet-type
weapons for use in Ukraine  and how
Cyprus is still punished by the U.S.
for refusing a similar request.
Henri: You know, understanding the place
that, that Cyprus had in that, in terms
of being stuck, they, they were certainly
weren't sanctioned, but they were still
being punished in a very specific way
for, and as far as I can just, it's
just not towing the American line.
It was just by, by just pushing back
as however, however minorly they did..
John Kirakou: That's the
exception to the rule.
You know, the only reason the Cypriots
have the great life and the great
country and great economy and and
honest democratic government that they
have is because they're a Western.
For all intents and purposes, they're
a western country, but you're right,
and 99.9% of Americans have no idea
that we've had a weapons embargo
on Cyprus for the last 46 years.
46 years sanctions on
Cyprus of all places.
Now, thank goodness that the likes of the
British and the French thought that was
ridiculous and that the Cipris deserved
an opportunity to protect themselves
against Turkish expansionism because God
knows the Americans never came through.
Henri: We did an episode a few months
ago on Fallujah, just the history of the
city as it pertained to the Iraq war,
Henri (2): Specifically regarding
Henri: the deaths of the American
mercenaries in Fallujah in March of '04.
Henri (2): Iraqi citizens were
asked some polling questions,
specifically about this ambush.
Henri: Why do you think this happened?
Is there anything that you can point to?
Henri (2): And the Iraqis were
very pointed in response, that they
knew the CIA had a long history in
Iraq from a multitude of incidents
and felt very strongly that these
Blackwater mercenaries, these plain
clothed con tractors could have
been members of the CIA and that
they were there to commit acts of
violence, to violate Iraqi sovereign
T as it had been many times before.
Henri: Now, understanding the long
section of US history on Iraq, I,
I don't know that you would want to
call them wrong, you know, in terms
of having that fear of not knowing.
And of course they're not told,
they didn't get told anything about.
What's actually happening in their
country, why the United States has
chosen to keep this regime even, you
know, we're now more than a decade
past the official end of the Iraq war,
and none of that has really changed.
I'm, I'm curious about, because you worked
on Iraq for, for such a long period of
time, and it was, uh, you know, in terms
of, you know, dealing with war on terror
and other things that, how, how do you
see places like that ever getting back
to anything that might seem normal?
John Kirakou: Yeah,
that's a good question.
And I, I think the very sad answer
is that they don't get back to
normal L look, look at the US
intervention in Iran in the 1950s.
Here we are 70 years later, 70 years
after we overthrew that government and
our relations still haven't returned to.
, we're still suffering from that
terrible foreign policy decision.
You know, one of the things that struck me
post nine 11 on Iraq, I, I was intimately
involved in the planning for the Iraq war.
I go into great detail about this
in my first book and, um, one of the
things that really struck me was how
these very important people at the
White House, uh, and in the, the power
structure at the Pentagon knew literally.
About Iraqi history, about
Iraqi culture and society.
I remember participating in a secure
video teleconference where one of
the deputy directors of the National
Security Council said, and this was the
day before we crossed the Iraqi border.
He said, when we crossed
that border tomorrow, they're
gonna throw flowers at us.
And I turned to my boss and I
said, was that a joke or did
they really know nothing about.
And the answer, I'm sorry to
say was that they knew nothing.
Henri: Thing to look back at and
especially like, you know, to, you
know, I, I, I, I realized looking
at the scope of it, you know,
that the, you know, I was an mp.
I was doing, you know,  ground stuff.
We were trained in the Iraqi police
and, and in terms of, but the, but once
you understand the full breadth of the
history, you know, you may have played,
and I mean you, in the royal sense, you
know, we, we may have played a very small
role, but we're still part of that giant
snowball that has crushed that country
that has been been a part of that.
Um, so I'd like to move on to talk a
little bit about, um, Whistleblowers
and specifically about, uh,
communications management, uh, units.
Um, that's been something that I've, I've
been reading about for quite a while.
I, I, um, but I, I saw your, your
blog post on your, and it, it got
me kind of thinking about it again.
Um, I was wondering if you could give
our listeners kind of a, a little basics
on communications management units.
John Kirakou: Yeah, so communications
management units are specialized units
inside the US Federal Prison system.
There are two of them, one.
is in the federal penitentiary
at Terre Haute, Indiana.
It used to be Federal Death Row.
They built a new death row and then
made the old death row into A C M U.
The other communications
management unit is at the Supermax
Prison in Marion, Illinois.
Now, the whole purpose of creating
a a a communications management.
Those are important.
Three important words.
That is a, a unit inside the most
secure prisons in America where
all communication with the outside
world can be controlled, right?
So you have Omar Ab, the
Blind Shake, who's now dead.
You don't want him communicating
with people on the outside.
So he can plan additional
terrorist attacks, right?
So you want him to be cut off?
We have the, the last surviving
Abu organization hijacker
from the 19, uh, eighties.
He's in the communications
management unit, John Gotti.
Uh, the, the boss of the
Gambino crime family died in a
communications management unit.
So these things were set up for the worst
of the worst, the most dangerous prison.
People who had to be were, were
the American people had to be
protected by, uh, from them, right?
But that's not really what they are.
Uh, they're used to silence
people whose messages are
inconvenient for the government.
And so you've got a
communications management unit.
Now that houses Daniel Hale,
the drone whistleblower.
Daniel, in my view, is a
bonafide American hero.
He's the one that told the American
people that the, that the drone
program run by whomever, D O D C
I A, nsc, whoever happens to be
pulling the trigger on any given day.
Was responsible for an 80%
death rate among civilians.
Okay, well, if it's a drone
program and it's be supposed
to be so much safer, right?
Then why are 80% of the
people you kill civilians?
They're AC accidental deaths.
He's the one that told us about that.
Now, he was sentenced not to
20 or 30 or 50 years in prison.
He was sentenced to 42 months.
Which, you know, with time off for
good behavior is under three years.
So if he's like so not dangerous that
he gets a prison sentence of less than
three years, why in the world is he
in a communications management unit?
Because the Justice Department was upset
with the shortness of his sentence.
Another one is Marty Gottesfeld.
Marty Gottesfeld was a computer hacker
and he read an article about a, a
little girl named Justine, uh, in,
uh, New England, who was born with
a genetic disorder, her parents took
her to Children's Hospital in Boston.
Uh, after their doctor said, look, we
can't help her anymore in our little town.
You should take her to
Children's in Boston.
The physicians at at Children's
Hospital in Boston said, oh, she
doesn't have this genetic disorder.
Uh, she's being abused and
starved by her parents.
So they seized this girl.
They arrested the parents.
And then a year later they're
like, oh, you know what?
She actually does have this disorder.
Uh, our bad, sorry.
You can release the parents now and
give them their other two kids back.
So in order to feel like he was helping
Marty initiated a, a directed denial
of service attack on the children's
Hospital fundraising website on the
weekend of its annual fundraiser.
Not only was that worth 10 years
in a maximum security penitentiary
and 2 million in, in, uh,
reparations to Children's Hospital,
but they put him in A C M U.
Now, do we really need to be protected
from Marty Godsfield that he's so
dangerous that we need to be, we need to
have him locked away, you know, forever.
Well, Marty gets out in two.
And he's gonna go back home to
Boston and live happily ever after.
There's no reason to have him in
a communications management unit.
Another one, I just got an email
from him today is Donald Reynolds.
Donald Reynolds is in a C M U serving a
sentence of triple life without parole
for a, a first time non-violent offense
related to the fast and furious scandel.
the reason he got Triple Life
without Parole is because he kept
turning down the Justice Department's
offers for lighter sentences because
he said, I didn't break the law.
So why would I take a plea
if I didn't break the law?
Okay?
You don't want to take a plea.
Not only are we gonna give you triple
life without parole, but you're gonna
spend the rest of your days in a
communications management unit with no
human contact for the rest of your life.
And that's what they did to him.
So these CMUs, these are, you know,
the United Nations has already declared
these CMUs to be forms of torture.
Right.
They're forms of torture.
They're cruel and unusual punishment,
and we, we use 'em anyway.
And it's worse than, it's
worse than just having your
communications, uh, blocked or banned.
You are locked 23 hours a day in,
uh, a six by 10 foot concrete cell.
Everything's made out
of either concrete or.
No windows.
That one hour a day, you're allowed
to go out through a little door.
It's about five feet high, and
you duck down and you go out this
little door, which opens up into
a cage on the outside, like a dog
cage, and you can walk in circles.
For an hour each day, and then
you go back into your cell.
If you receive mail, you can't actually
physically hold the mail or receive it.
They project your mail on a, on
a TV monitor up at the ceiling.
So it's so high up you can't touch it.
So you can't like break it and
you know, take the glass and
cut your throat or something.
They'll leave the mail available
for you for five minutes and
then they take it down and it's.
No tv, no radio, no phone.
You're allowed one call a month,
but it, it's only to your attorney.
You can't call your wife, your
kids, your friends, nothing.
Just your attorney.
And that's where we put, you
know, some of the most important
whistleblowers that we have.
Henri: I'm, I'm curious, the large
number of whistleblowers that have
come forward in the post nine 11
Global War on Terror era that.
Why do you think, um, you know,
why did the War on Terror and the
war on whistleblowers coincide?
And why do you think so many of
them have been produced by the
same, the same circumstances?
John Kirakou: Yeah, I, I can, I can
give you a very clear answer to that.
Um, and that was, That
was, uh, John Brennan.
So there, there've always
been whistleblowers through
modern American history.
Um, post nine 11, they became
particularly newsworthy, right?
And, um, the George W.
Bush administration initiated criminal
investigations of two whistleblowers.
Tom Drake from N S A and Jeffrey
Sterling from c I a, but it was the
Obama administration that just launched
an all out open war on whistleblowers.
That's because of John Brennan.
John Brennan became the Deputy National
Security Advisor for counterterrorism.
In Obama's first term, and
he became CIA director.
In Obama's second term, John
Brennan had a nixonian obsession
with national security leaks, and
it was John Brennan who convinced
Barack Obama to use the Antiquated
Espionage Act as a , as an iron fist.
To, to crush whistleblowers.
Uh, a New York Times journalist told
me that on the day of my arrest,
every single one of the New York Times
national security sources went silent,
and they stayed silent for six months.
Well, that was the point.
Of prosecuting me and prosecuting
seven other whistleblowers, uh,
during the Obama administration.
It wasn't necessarily to
teach John Kiriakou a lesson,
frankly, they made me famous.
Right.
They elevated me to this position
of like national human rights
spokesman, anti torture spokesman.
They made me famous.
They, they opened, uh, doors and
created opportunities for me that
I otherwise never would've had.
I would be, I would be wrapping up a
career in some cubicle somewhere if
they hadn't, uh, ordered my arrest.
Uh, in, in a funny way, I'm,
I'm kind of glad they did
because I think I've, I've done.
More important work because of my arrest.
Um, and I wanna say something about
the, uh, the Espionage Act too.
Henri, I think, I think the
Espionage Act is very important.
It's something that Americans really
need to know about the Espionage Act.
Was written in 1917, passed into
law in 1917 to combat German
saboteurs during the First World War.
Uh, it was used right after passage
to, to incarcerate people who were
opposed to us entry into the war.
Uh, most famously, Eugene v Debs,
the head of the Socialist Party,
he actually ran for president from
his prison cell, uh, at the, at.
Maximum security penitentiary in Atlanta.
Uh, a Hollywood producer was arrested
and charged with espionage and served
five years because a movie that
he made was deemed to be not pro
British enough during World War I.
So between 1917 and January of 2009,
three Americans were charged with
espionage for speaking to the media.
Three Americans were charged
with espionage for speaking to
the media between 1917 and 2009.
In just the eight years of the Obama
presidency, eight of us were charged
with espionage for speaking to the
media, and then under Donald Trump,
another four were charged with espionage.
You know, beginning with, with me,
the sentences got longer and longer
and longer for each person after me.
I was sitting with Tom Drake in
Daniel, Hale's, uh, sentencing
hearing a year ago, October.
And, um, much to my Shock, my
name came up in sentencing and.
The prosecution said that they wanted,
I think they were asking for 40 years
in prison for Daniel and Daniel's
attorney said that they were asking for
the same sentence that Kiriakou got.
I got 30 months and I served 23,
and then the judge said that Jeffrey
Sterling got Kiriakou plus 12 months
because Jeffrey Sterling went to trial.
And then the judge said that he's gone
over the numbers and he's gonna give
Daniel ...kiriakou plus 16 months.
And I'm just sitting there and, and I'm
sitting, like, I'm sitting with Tom Drake.
And then immediately in front of me are
three journalists from the Washington
Post, the New York Times, and Politico.
And they were like, you care to comment?
And I said, yeah, he should have been.
He should have been release.
You know, with, with time served,
he doesn't belong in prison.
We, we should be making statues
to people like him, not sending
them to communications management
units to make matters worse.
Um, the judge recommended very strongly
in that sentencing hearing that
Daniel be sent to the low security
prison in, uh, Butner, North Carolina.
He has a substance abuse problem,
problem, and the Federal Bureau of Prisons
has this program called R D A P, the
Residential Drug and Alcohol Program.
And if you go through RDAP,
which is basically just sitting and
watching episodes of intervention.
And I mean that quite, quite literally.
That's, that's what rdap is.
And they say, you know,
drugs don't do 'em.
Now watch this episode of intervention.
And when you watch the whole
whatever it is, 20 episodes, you
get a year off your sentence.
So I said to Daniel, before you
went to prison, listen, this 42
months, this is a victory because
you get 15% off for good behavior.
And then you get another year
off for R D A P, I said, and
you're in a low security prison.
You're just gonna lay there and
read books and watch tv, and you're
gonna be home before you know it.
Instead, they sent him to the maximum
security penitentiary at Marion, Illinois
and then put him in the C M U on top of
that, which makes him ineligible for RDAP.
So he's gonna do the whole 42 months.
Henri: Even.
Even with with good behavior
time that be, do they, do they
curtail that for people in cmu?
John Kirakou: well, they, they'll, they
technically calculate it for people in
CMUs, but Marty Gottesfeld has already
lost all of his good behavior time
because he did terrible, terrible things
like write a letter to a journalist.
But God forbid, And then in in
a phone call to his attorney, he
asked the attorney, would you call
my wife and tell her that I'm okay?
Oh, that's a third party communication.
We're taking away all of
your good behavior time.
So it's tough.
They do it on purpose.
You know, in my own sentencing, the, the
judge, um, ordered that I'd be sent to
a minimum security work camp and in a
minimum security camp, there are no, there
are no fences, no bars on the windows.
The doors are never locked.
You work in town, like
there's a university in town.
You go sweep the floors or whatever.
You're just on your honor, not to abscond.
The Justice Department
was furious that the.
Order that I be sent to
a minimum security camp.
So they arbitrarily just sent me
to the regular prison that was
across the street from the camp.
And they said that they did that because
I was a trained c I A officer, which
made me a national security threat.
Well, if I was a threat, then
why don't you send me to a
maximum security penitentiary
if you think I'm so dangerous?
So what I ended up doing was I, I ended.
Um, saying yes to every
interview request I ever had.
Jake Tapper drove to the prison and
interviewed me for c n Um, I gave
multiple interviews to N P R, um, a B C.
News came, I mean, it was just count.
I can't tell you how many
Greek newspapers came.
I, I'm a, I'm a big star in Greece cuz I
stood up to the American government and
I, I happen to be a dual US Greek citizen,
but, They complained and complained and
complained about all the media contact
that I had and I said, listen, I'll
tell you guys the honest to God's truth.
I told the warden this
straight to his face.
I said, I was told I was gonna be sent
to the minimum security camp across
the street, and if I had gone to that
camp, you would've never heard about me.
I would've just kept my head down.
I would've kept my mouth shut.
I would've done my 23 months and
I would've gone home, but you
guys had to be dicks about it.
You guys had to make an issue about
it, and so I decided that I am going
to exercise my constitutional rights,
which I have not given up to speak
with the press and to speak free.
And that's what I did.
I was a thorn in their side from the very
beginning, just like Marty Gottesfeld did.
Is Daniel's not Daniel, just wants to
keep his head down and come home, which I
totally respect, but for me, not a chance.
Henri: I would ask about the, you know,
the, the, the bureaucracy that's able
to get away with these kind of decisions
that the, the, um, you know, placing in,
uh, and I don't know if this is common
for all whistleblowers, but I assume some
form of it is placing the restrictions.
On reality winner as to telling her own
story after she got out of prison that now
she's bound to this agreement infinitely.
You know, I, I, I guess I wonder about,
you know, that the, the e entirely
seems, you know, a la entire lack of
due process and the entire lack of,
uh, equal protection under the law.
How, how do, how are they able to
continue this and, and do you feel
that there's big steps that be, can
be taken to rectify it in some way?
John Kirakou: Oh, yeah.
Uh, reality.
Reality, and I have talked about this.
Her judge seriously overreached by, by
infringing on her constitutional rights,
I don't think that would stand up in
court for two minutes, but she's afraid
to challenge it because they could
technically still send her back to prison.
Um, by violating her, they'll,
they say that she, uh, she broke
the terms of her release and they
violate her, uh, federal probation
and they send her back to prison.
So she just wants to get through it.
She doesn't wanna challenge
it when I get outta prison.
Um, they told me that I had 30 days
to find a job or I go back to prison.
And so, I was offered a job at a think
tank, the oldest progressive think
tank in Washington, the Institute for
Policy Studies, and they wanted me
to write about, um, about, uh, these,
these sentencing reform and judicial
reform and prison reform issues.
I said, great.
I took the job and I had to.
Permission from the Bureau of Prisons,
which is supposed to be proforma.
Well, they denied.
They denied my request and they said
that it was inappropriate that Mr.
Kiriakou be commenting on prison issues.
So I said, you know what?
Violate me.
Send me back I'll have every news
network in America camped out in
the prison parking lot, violate me.
And I took the job.
And there was some, you know, huffing
and puffing, but they backed down.
Um, I, I think that reality, if, if
she wanted to, uh, to challenge these
draconian, uh, uh, reigns that they
have on her ability to make a living
and to speak freely and to talk about
her case and herself, I think she would.
But, but I understand, you know,
challenging them is not for everybody..
Henri: So what, um, what's to be done?
You know, what if, if, if John Kiriakou
had the power today, what would you do to
rectify some of this, some of this stuff?
John Kirakou: Uh, you gotta start from
scratch by tearing down the entire system.
You know, uh, the, the whoever happens
to be president at any given time,
when it comes time to appoint a new
director of the Bureau of Prisons, they
just appoint the same kind of person.
One after the other.
After the other.
The current one used to be the head
of the Oregon State Prison System.
Big deal.
The, the guy before her was the deputy
director of the Bureau of Prisons.
The guy before him was a warden,
and then the deputy Director
of the Bureau of Prisons.
The guy before him was a general, a
brigadier general who was in charge
of the military prison system.
Well, we need.
We need fresh thinking, fresh ideas.
There was a warden in, in Maine,
for example, uh, prisoners were
complaining about the quality of
food, which is not human grade food.
It's animal feed grade food
that's fed to prisoners.
And so the prison was sitting on
this giant, you know, 50 acre, a
hundred acre parcel of property.
And so the people who were in the minimum
security, he taught them how to farm.
And not only now does that prison, is
that prison completely self-sufficient
in terms of fruits and vegetables,
but they're able to sell their
excess fruits and vegetables in town.
That's the kind of thinking that
we need in the prison system.
Now, one of the things that made me
very happy, Two years ago was Hakeem
Jeffries, who's now the Democratic
leader in the House of Representatives.
Hakeem Jeffries worked with, um,
Marco Rubio to push through a bill
that mandated sentencing reform.
I, I can't stress how, how gutsy that is.
Can you imagine you're a, you're a,
an elected member of the House of
Representatives, you've gotta run for
reelection every two years, and you
go out on the campaign trail and you
say, I'm going to pass a bill to make
it harder to keep people in prison.
Well, how many votes is
that gonna win you now?
That's exactly what needs to be done.
But those two, were the only ones with
the balls to actually go out and do it.
So we need that kind of
bipartisan legislation.
And let me ask a rhetorical question too.
How come the Germans got it right
and the Danes and the Swedes and
the Norwegians and the Fins, you
know, how come they got it right?
How come they have recidivism rates
of 10 and 15% when ours are 50?
Why is it the UN declares our prisons
to be sources of torture, but their
prisons are set up like apartments where
you teach people life skills so that
when they go back out, they don't sell
drugs and they don't rob gas stations
and they know how to, you know, run a
load of laundry and balance a checkbook
because that's what they're taught to.
So we are, uh, the, the, the prison system
that we have at every level, level, you
know, city and county, state and federal.
It's a system that we should be
ashamed of, not something that we
should hope others would aspire to.
We, ours is an embarrassment.
John Kiriakou: So, um, my, uh, my
last question for you, um, this is
kind of, kind of similar to what we've
been talking about, but also kind of
different that the um, What has been
your, your observation of the American,
um, film industry at television
industry in the period for the global
war on terror in terms of their, their
acquiescence to stories that are jive
easily with, with government narratives?
Great question.
Uh, thank you for that question.
Um, as a.
Ever since 2007, I've been
writing television pilots and
I've actually sold eight of them.
That's amazing.
That's awesome.
Yeah, it's been a lot of fun.
I was the script advisor
on the Bourne Ultimatum.
on to Paris with Love.
I was the script advisor on um,
kill the Messenger, and I was
the security advisor on the kite.
And I'm, I'm just now, we
just finished season one.
I'm the script advisor on a new show on
CBS that's coming out in February called
The True Lies based on the James Cameron,
uh, movie of the same, of the same title.
So I'm kind of acquainted with the way
these things play out in Hollywood, and
I'll tell you that the easy answer is that
the CIA finally got wise to something that
the f b I learned way back in the fifties.
And that's that you have to
control the narrative, right?
Have you ever seen.
A film not done by Oliver Stone
where the CIA's the bad guy?
No.
They don't exist.
It's gotten to the point where,
um, just after the invasion of
Iraq, the CIA's Office of Public
Affairs opened up a branch inside
Public Affairs whose sole duty it
is to liaise with Hollywood Studio.
So you want a classified briefing,
uh, over a classified mockup of the
bin Laden compound, ala zero dark 30.
Come on.
And we'll tell you our side of the story.
And then that's the side that you
write up as the script for the
movie, and we'll give you free
access to the building, right?
You wanna make a movie that perpetuates
the lie that the torture program resulted.
In the, the capture, not capture, but
the killing of Osama bin Laden, that it
was torture that led us to his location.
You, you, you want that lie to be
perpetuated, then come on, we'll
give you classified briefings
and you can interview the, the
analysts and do whatever you want.
Just like in the fifties, the sixties,
and the early seventies where every
single movie and TV show about the F
B I was pro F B I because Jay Edgar
Hoover had to approve every single.
Well, now you've got the CIA
that has a hand in every single
script for every movie that has
something to do with the cia.
It's just wrong.
Henri: Something we do pretty
frequently on the podcast is we
talk to, uh, Tom Secker, I don't
know if you're familiar with him.
He runs, uh, spyculture.com yeah.
I think it's one of the most grotesque
aspects of our modern military
industrial complex that they are able
to stick their fingers so deeply into
what is otherwise entirely fiction.
Mm-hmm.
and create these narratives that.
Absent in the other point
of reference, people learn a
lot from movies and TV shows.
Sure they do.
Should they?
I don't, I don't know about
that, but they certainly do.
I know that the things that I knew
about the military before I joined
were all came from those movies.
I saw, you know, the, the Rock, black Hawk
Down, all these, you know, different ones.
Um, But that the, the enormous
power they have and how it, how it
seems to directly butt up against
any kind of First amendment.
Supposed to actually have the
benefit of free speech as Americans.
One that extends to filmmakers too.
And granted, you know, there's corporate
interest and other things involved too.
John Kiriakou: Sure.
Henri: But, you know, um, listening
to a, a podcast, um, on North Korea
recently a, uh, a director, someone who
had, uh, she had gone to North Korea
and directed a film, and she was talking
about the comparison of North Korea.
Uh, desire of involvement with her
film, which was almost nonexistent.
Henri (2): Switch to the American
cinematic landscape, where U.S.
filmmakers allow huge changes in their
scripts and presentations, in order
to receive D O D or CIA support, and
it's a blatant act of censorship,
withholding their support such as
helicopters or other major equipment
and filming locations if the filmmakers
don't properly tow the government line.
Deciding what can and
can't be in the film.
Henri: Do this and I couldn't do this.
And, you know, you get narrowed down
into telling a story that is exactly the
story they want told, not anything that
is actually controlled by the filmmaker
or can be seen as truth by the audience.
It locks us into these mindsets of
being accepting of violence as the
first solution of being accepting, of
seeing American troops in places that we
would, you wouldn't think they would be.
John Kiriakou: It's absolutely right.
Henri: There's never going to be
a really large change in the winds
of how America does its foreign
policy until, I think, until that's
rectified in some more powerful way.
John Kiriakou: Mm-hmm.
Henri: certainly at the top of whistle
whistleblowers goes right alongside that.
But, you know, it is, it, it's what,
what people run on, you know, is the,
the things, you know, my wife and I,
we sit down every night and we watch
new stuff, but now we understand
that we're not just dealing with the
desires and, and whims of filmmakers
and writers and things like that.
We're dealing with them literally
having military or intelligence.
I wouldn't call 'em overlords, overseers,
I guess would be a better way to put it.
Just saying, this is okay
and this is not okay.
Mm-hmm.
. Um, and it's, and it's,
it's just disgusting.
I had another experience with a buddy who.
You know, the, uh, the National
Geographic series, the Long Road Home.
John Kiriakou: Sure.
Henri: A friend of mine, who deployed
to Baghdad in early 2004, his unit saw
action during early April that year that
was portrayed in The Long Road Home.
I traveled to his home in New York
and together, we watched that and we
recorded some of his responses from it.
And just to see, you know, just basic
things that were just not right.
Pretending that there were suicide
bombers in Kosovo was one that
I I, that I could never, oh man.
That made me so angry.
John Kiriakou: Oh, yes.
Henri: But, um, anyway, I think
that's probably, uh, a good place
for us to, uh, wrap it up for today.
John Kiriakou: You asked very smart
questions, very, very on point
questions, so thank you for that.
I would ask one favor if, if anybody's
interested in these issues, I just
migrated over to Substack It's john
kiriakou.dot com so thanks very much.
It was a, it was a
pleasure to speak with you.
Henri: I, I really enjoyed it too, John.
I am, I am actually a new, uh, a
new subscriber to your Substack.
I've really enjoyed it so far, and,
uh, I hope to have you back sometime.
John Kiriakou: I look forward to that.
Thanks very much for the invitation.
Henri: All right, thanks John.
And, uh, thank you everyone
for listening today.
We'll, uh, we'll catch you next time.
Take care.
Money is tight these days for everyone.
Penny pinching to make it through the
month often doesn't give people the funds
to contribute to a creator they support.
So we consider it the highest honor
that folks help us fund the podcast
in any dollar amount they're able.
Patreon is the main place to do that.
And for supporters who can donate $10
a month or more, they will be listed
right here as an honorary producer.
Like these fine folks.
Fahim Shirazee, James O'Barr, James
Higgins, Eric Phillips, Paul Appell,
Julie Dupree, Thomas Benson, Janet
Hanson, Daniel Fleming, Michael
Karon, Ren Jacob, Howard Reynolds,
Rick Coffee, scott spaulding, Spooky
Tooth, and the Statist Quo podcast.
However, if Patreon isn't your style, you
can contribute directly through PayPal
at PayPal dot me forward slash Fortress
on hill, or please check out our store on
Spreadshirt for some great Fortress merch.
We're on Twitter and @facebook.com
at Fortress On A Hill.
You can find our full collection of
episodes at Fortress On A Hill dot com.
Skepticism is one's best armor.
Never forget it.
We'll see you next time.
I hope you'll pay attention.
I will not detain you long.